Guide to the Afrika Bambaataa hip hop archive, circa 1972-2016.
Afrika Bambaataa hip hop archive,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Afrika Bambaataa hip hop archive, circa 1972-2016.
8094
Afrika Bambaataa, 1957-
600 cubic feet.
Vinyl records and other A/V Recordings, Financial Records, Manuscripts, Memorabilia, Photocopies, Photographs, Printed Materials, Publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Approximately 40,000 sound recordings representing Bambaataa's music collection from the 1970s to the present. The archive also includes books, documents, and files relating to the founding and spread of the Universal Zulu Nation; and videos, papers, and clothing.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Afrika Bambaataa is an American disc jockey, singer, and songwriter from the South Bronx, New York. Often called the “Godfather” of Hip Hop, Bambaataa has helped to define Hip Hop since it emerged in the South Bronx in the 1970s. One of a handful of Hip Hop's 1970s originators, Bambaataa gave Hip Hop its name, and was the first to define its core artistic elements - DJing, rapping, break dancing, and graffiti art - under one cultural umbrella. His cultural organization, the Universal Zulu Nation, has helped to spread Hip Hop culture throughout the world. His genre-defining 1982 song "Planet Rock" and subsequent electro-funk tracks have become icons of hip-hop and electronic music. In 2007 he was nominated for induction into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Approximately 40,000 sound recordings representing Bambaataa's music collection from the 1970s to the present. The archive also includes books, documents, and files relating to the founding and spread of the Universal Zulu Nation; and videos, papers, and clothing.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Afrika Bambaataa, 1957-; Universal Zulu Nation (Organization)
Subjects:
African American youth -- Social life and customs.; Disc jockeys.; Electronic music.; Funk (Music).; Hip-hop.; Hip-hop -- Influence.; Hip-hop -- History. -- United States; Music -- Social aspects.; Race relations.; Rap (Music); Rap (Music) -- Political aspects.; Rap musicians.; Hip-hop -- New York.; Rap (Music) -- New York.; Hip-hop; Rap (Music); Rap musicians; Social history
Places:
Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Social conditions -- 20th century.; New York (State) -- New York; New York (State) -- Bronx; United States
Form and Genre Terms:
History
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to collection restricted until completion of processing, with the exception of vinyl records that have been individually cataloged.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Manuscripts
a. School Papers and Assignments
b. Africa Trip
c. Soul Scrapbooks and Music Writing
d. Notebooks and Miscellaneous Manuscripts
e. Lyrics and Poems
f. Bronx River Neighborhood Center
g. Phone and Contact Lists
Series II. Flyers
Series III. Photographs
Series IV. Personal Papers
a. Personal Papers
b. Press About Bambaataa
c. Catalogs and Mail
Series V. Universal Zulu Nation Documents
a. Infinity Lessons
b. Administration
Series VI. Stage Costumes and Clothing
Series VII. Periodicals and Publications
a. Small Press Publications
b. Periodicals
c. Publications from 3410 De Reimer Ave. Bronx, NY
d. Other Publications
Series VIII. Moving images and audio recordings
a. Video cassettes
a. Audio cassettes
Series IX. Music collection
12 inch vinyl
Sureshots and altered/obscured
Numbered by Bambaataa
Annotated, not numbered (Alphabetical by artist)
A-D
E-H
I-L
L-O
P-S
T-Z
Numbers, unknown and various
Second alpha sequence
Cataloged individually
Not annotated (Alphabetical by artist)
A
B
C
D
E
F
G
H
I
J
K
L
M
N
O
P
Q
R
S
Afrika Bambaataa recordings
Renegades of Rhythm Tour
Test pressings and white labels (not yet cataloged)
Compilations (not yet cataloged)
7 inch vinyl
Numbered (not yet cataloged)
Annotated not numbered (not yet cataloged)
No annotations (not yet cataloged)
Acetates and lacquer discs
Cassettes (not yet cataloged)
CDs (not yet cataloged)
Series X. Ephemera
CONTAINER LIST
- Series IX. Music collection
  - 12 inch Vinyl
    - Zulu Nation Sure Shots and labels obscured
      Series contains vinyl discs and jackets where the labels of the vinyl or the jacket was obscured with tape, white labels, black ink, or scratched so that the artist and title is not recognizable. This was likely done in order to keep this information secret from other DJs. Many of these vinyl discs are also marked “Zulu Nation Sure Shot” indicating that this is a record that is sure to get the crowd dancing.
      Arranged by box number.
      - Josephine superstar, Expression; SR-7089; Rashad, Phylicia, 1948- (Box 7)
        Promotional copy.
        Casablanca Records
        Los Angeles, California
      - Man and his music, 1986; SR-7470-7471; Cooke, Sam. (Box 15)
        RCA / Ariola
        Germany
      - Original music from the motion picture Sunnyside, 1979; SR-7166-7167; New York City Band. (Box 18)
        American International Records
      - Can't you see I'm fired up; Eyeballin', 1979; SR-8897-8898; Mass Production (Musical group) (Box 140)
        Promotional copy._x000D_ From the Cotillion LP 5211, In the purest form.
        Cotillion Records
        New York, New York
      - Changin' times, 1976; SR-8929-8930; White, Ike. (Box 140)
        Includes quote from Stevie Wonder on container: "There are many "Ike Whites" in this world - let's give these men a fare - making not the color of his skin his final fate for being behind bars."_x000D_
        Landmark Entertainment Committee
        North Miami Beach, Florida
      - Jeff Beck with the Jan Hammer Group live, 1977; SR-8977-8978; Beck, Jeff, (Box 140)
        CBS
      - Lucumi, macumba, voodoo, 1978; SR-9032; Palmieri, Eddie. (Box 140)
        Epic
        United States
      - Sunshine love; Sunshine love: long version, 1976; SR-8669-8670; Sciscente, Dominic, (Box 141)
        Special 12 inch disco mix.
        RCA Victor
        Canada
      - Rim arrives, 1980; SR-9667-9668; Obeng, Rim Kwaku. (Box 141)
        Rising Times
      - Loadstone., 1969; SR-9669-9670; Loadstone (Musical group) (Box 141)
        Barnaby Records
      - Everyday people: the breakbeat party album, 2004; SR-7144-7145; Afrika Bambaataa, 1957- (Box 164)
        Pickwick International Productions
        London, England
      - Mind control: (The Danmass remixes), 1997; SR-7148-7149; Afrika Bambaataa, 1957- (Box 164)
        Dunhill Records
      - Hydraulic funk; Flashlight, 1999; SR-7260-7262; Hydraulic Funk (Musical group) (Box 164)
      - Avalanche., 1976; SR-8885-8886; Avalanche (Musical group) (Box 459)
        ABC Records
      - More of the monkees, 1967; SR-8921,8944; Monkees (Musical group), (Box 459)
        Colgems
        New York
      - Excitable boy, 1978; SR-8922-8923; Zevon, Warren. (Box 459)
        Asylum
      - I wish I knew, 1968; SR-8924 (Box 459)
        Publisher number on disc label: 8185_x000D_
        Atlantic Records
      - Mixin' it up., 1980; SR-8925-8926 (Box 459)
        Matrix / Runout (Side 1 Label): ST-A-80 444 1 Matrix / Runout (Side 2 Label): ST-A-80 444 2.
      - Bride stripped bare, 1978; SR-8927-8928; Ferry, Bryan. (Box 459)
        Matrix / Runout (Side One Label): ST A 784127 Matrix / Runout (Side Two Label): ST A 784128.
      - Crash and burn., 1980; SR-8931-8932; Travers, Pat. (Box 459)
        Polydor Records
      - Temporary music, 1979; SR-8933; Material (Musical group) (Box 459)
        Red Records
        Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
      - Sex., 1981; SR-8934; Telex (Musical group) (Box 459)
        PVC
        Brussels, Belgium
      - Sex, 1981; SR-8935; Telex (Musical group) (Box 459)
        Ariola
      - To each ..., 1981; SR-8936-8937; Certain Ratio (Musical group) (Box 459)
        Expanded Music: DFC
        Bologna, Italy
      - Blackfoot strikes., 1979; SR-8938-8939 (Box 459)
        Matrix / Runout (Label Side 1): ST-C-794223-PR; Matrix / Runout (Label Side 2): ST-C-794224-PR.
        Atco Records
      - Warhead (long version); Lexington queen, 1980; SR-8940-8941; Sakamoto, Ryu¿¿ichi, 1952- (Box 459)
        Matrix / Runout (Runout side A): 12 WIP 6723 A-10 9 GRAEME-SOUND CLINIC; Matrix / Runout (Runout side B): 12 WIP 6723 B-10 9.
        Island Records
      - X factor, 1978; SR-8942; White, Michael, 1933- (Box 459)
        Elektra Records
      - You are my heartbeat; X factor, 1978; SR-8943; White, Michael, 1933- (Box 459)
        Matrix / Runout: AS-11391 A - SP; Matrix / Runout: AS-11391 B - SP.
      - Straight up funk go go style., 1981; SR-8945; Trouble Funk (Musical group) (Box 459)
        TF Records
      - Straight up funk go go style, 1981; SR-8946; Trouble Funk (Musical group) (Box 459)
        Jamtu Records
        Cherry Hill, New Jersey
      - Take it easy; Shake me, 2001; SR-8947; Mint Royale (Musical group) (Box 459)
        Factory
      - As the time goes by, 1981; SR-8948-8949; Funkapolitan (Musical group) (Box 459)
        London Records
      - You and me just started, 1982; SR-8950-8951; Taylor, Linda (Vocalist), (Box 459)
        Greensleeves
      - Goosebumps; Underfire, 1981; SR-8952-8953; Dejean, Debra, (Box 459)
        Hallmark Records
        Cricklewood, London
      - Cutie pie, 1981; SR-8954-8955; Dayton (Musical group) (Box 459)
        Matrix / Runout (Side 1: Runout, Hand Etched): SP-1-209-Z-1; Matrix / Runout (Side 2: Runout, Hand Etched): SP-12-209-Z-1.
        Liberty
        Hollywood, California
      - American songs, 1981; SR-8956; Material (Musical group) (Box 459)
        Brooklyn, New York
      - Glitterhouse., 1981; SR-8957; Medium Medium (Musical group) (Box 459)
        Cherry Red/Cachalot Records: Marketed by Jem Records
        South Plainfield, New Jersey
      - Success and failure, 1976; SR-8958-8959; Stovall, Gary D. (Box 459)
      - Find a way; Ride the pressure (plenty of fun mix), 1990; SR-8960; Coldcut (Musical group) (Box 459)
        Ahead of Our Time
        England
      - Don't stop the music., 1981; SR-8961-8962 (Box 459)
        Mango Records
      - For sweet people from Sweet Charles., 1974; SR-8963-8964 (Box 459)
        Pebblegroove; Distributed by Holborne Dist. Co. Ltd.
        Barbados
        Mount Albert, Onterio
      - Hot plate. 1., 1987; SR-8965 (Box 459)
        Matrix / Runout (A side): HOTHED-101 A1* Pa-2627-MT KICK HIM OUT; Matrix / Runout (B side): HOTHED-101 AA1* Pa-2627-MT.
      - Solid ground, 1981; SR-8966-8967; Laws, Ronnie. (Box 459)
      - People music., 1973; SR-8968 (Box 459)
        People Records
        Polydor
      - Straight up funk go go style., 1981; SR-8969-8970; Trouble Funk (Musical group) (Box 459)
      - Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1967; SR-8971-8972; Beatles, (Box 459)
        Capitol Records
      - Liquid Liquid., 1981; SR-8973-8974; Liquid Liquid (Musical group) (Box 459)
        99 Records
      - CTI summer jazz at the Hollywood Bowl, Live two: CTI All-Stars., 1977; SR-8975 (Box 459)
        CTI Records: CTI 7077._x000D_
        CTI Records
      - Kenny., 1979; SR-8976; Rogers, Kenny. (Box 459)
        United Artists Records
      - Visage., 1981; SR-9036; Visage (Musical group) (Box 459)
      - Final comedown: original motion picture soundtrack, 1972; SR-8867-8868; Marcus, Wade. (Box 460)
        Blue Note
      - Comin' at ya., 1976; SR-8871-8872; Escovedo, Coke. (Box 460)
        Mercury Records
        Chicago, Illinois
      - Time is the key, 1979; SR-8873; Gong (Musical group) (Box 460)
        Arista Records
      - Joy, 1973; SR-8874-8875; Hayes, Isaac. (Box 460)
        Enterprise
        Memphis, Tennessee
      - Layers, 1973; SR-8876-8877-8878; McCann, Les, 1935- (Box 460)
      - Fat boys, 1984; SR-8879-8880; Disco 3 (Musical group) (Box 460)
        Sutra Records
      - This time; A chocolate jam, 1979; SR-8881-8882; Chancler, Ndugu, (Box 460)
        "Demonstration. Not for sale."
      - Lalabye, 1977; SR-8883-8884; Rosenthal, Hilton, (Box 460)
        Tom n' Jerry Records: Salsoul Records
      - (You've got) My love, my life, my soul; I want you around me, 1978; SR-8887-8888; McCrae, George. (Box 460)
        T.K. Disco
        Hialeah, Florida
      - Don's place; Soul Train theme '79, 1979; SR-8889; Hollywood Disco Jazz Band (Box 460)
        A&M Disco
      - Don's place, 1979; SR-889; Hollywood Disco Jazz Band (Box 460)
        Promotion not for sale._x000D_
      - Fool for the city, 1975; SR-8891-8892; Foghat (Musical group) (Box 460)
        Bearsville Records
      - Street corner stuff, 1977; SR-8893-8894; Peddler (Musical group) (Box 460)
        United Artists Records/Chi Sound Records
      - Man incognito, 1976; SR-8895-8896; Mouzon, Alphonse. (Box 460)
      - I got a magic feeling making love, 1979; SR-8899; Zulu Gang (Musical group) (Box 460)
        AB Productions
        France
      - I got a magic feeling making love, 1979; SR-8900; Zulu Gang (Musical group) (Box 460)
      - Hold me, touch me, 1977; SR-8901; Bernier, Californiarolyne. (Box 460)
        Private Stock Records
      - Hold me, touch me, 1977; SR-8902; Bernier, Californiarolyne. (Box 460)
        Deram
      - Street dance; Music, harmony and rhythm, 1977; SR-8903-8904; Brooklyn Dreams (Musical group) (Box 460)
        Millennium
      - Ain't we funkin' now, 1978; SR-8905-8906; Brothers Johnson, (Box 460)
        Promotional copy._x000D_ From the A&M album "BLAM!" SP-4714.
        A&M Records
        Santa Monica, California
      - Jamerican man, 1977; SR-8907-8908; Oliver, David (Vocalist) (Box 460)
      - Nassau Day; Midnight plane, 1978; SR-8909-8910 (Box 460)
        Columbia Records
      - Primal scream, 1976; SR-8911-8912; Ferguson, Maynard. (Box 460)
      - Cheap Trick at Budokan, 1979; SR-8913-8914; Cheap Trick (Musical group) (Box 460)
      - What is it, 1970; SR-8915-8916; S.O.U.L. (Musical group) (Box 460)
        Music Tree Corporation
        Atlanta, Georgia
      - Shine; Give it up, 1978; SR-8917-8918; Bar-Kays (Musical group) (Box 460)
      - Sky's the limit, 1978; SR-8919-8920 (Box 460)
      - I don't want to be a freak (But I can't help myself); Your piece of the rock, 1979; SR-8979; Dynasty (Musical group) (Box 460)
        Promotional copy; not for sale._x000D_
        Solar Records
      - Isley's greatest hits., 1973; SR-8980; Isley Brothers. (Box 460)
        T-Neck Records
      - Wheel me out; Hello operator...I mean dad...I mean police...I can't even remember who I am, 1980; SR-8981-8982; Was (Not Was) (Musical group) (Box 460)
        Antilles
      - Soul is-- Pretty Purdie, 1972; SR-8983-8984; Purdie, Bernard. (Box 460)
        Flying Dutchman
      - Good times (dance mix); Good times; Superstition, 1982; SR-8987-8988; Drinking Electricity (Musical group) (Box 460)
        Survival
      - Malik, 1976; SR-6965; Lafayette Afro Rock Band. (Box 461)
        Mainstream Records
      - Love is the message., 1981; SR-6969 (Box 461)
        Hilary
        Trinidad & Tobago
      - Time is the key, 1979; SR-7137; Gong (Musical group) (Box 461)
      - Here's to good friends, 1978; SR-8016-8017; Prysock, Arthur. (Box 461)
        MCA Records
        Universal City, California
      - Isis., 1974; SR-8989; Isis (Musical group) (Box 461)
        Buddah Records
      - Barretto power, 1972; SR-8990-8991; Barretto, Ray. (Box 461)
        Fania Records
      - Changes, 1979; SR-8992-8993; Blue Velvets (Soul group) (Box 461)
        Record Symphony Corporation
      - Browne sugar, 1979; SR-8994-8995; Browne, Tom (Trumpet player) (Box 461)
        GRP Crescendo
        S.l.
      - Places and spaces, 1975; SR-8996-8997; Byrd, Donald. (Box 461)
      - Pieces of eight, 1978; SR-8998-8999; Styx (Musical group) (Box 461)
      - Crown International Pictures presents "Van Nuys Blvd.": original soundtrack, 1979; SR-9000-9001; Wright, Ron (Composer) (Box 461)
      - Blackbyrds., 1974; SR-9002-9003; Blackbyrds (Musical group) (Box 461)
        Fantasy Records
        Berkeley, California
      - Balcones Fault., 1977; SR-9004-9005; Balcones Fault (Musical group) (Box 461)
        Cotique
      - Stiffs live., 1978; SR-9006-9007 (Box 461)
        Stiff Records
      - Lost man: original soundtrack, 1969; SR-9008; Jones, Quincy, 1933- (Box 461)
        UNI Records
      - Mary Wilson., 1979; SR-9010-9011; Wilson, Mary (Vocalist) (Box 461)
        Motown Records
      - Movin on, 1979; SR-9012-9013; Robinson, Vicki Sue. (Box 461)
        RCA Records
      - Queen Samantha 2., 1979; SR-9014-9015; Queen Samantha. (Box 461)
        Marlin
        Miami, Florida
      - Work to live don't live to work., 1981; SR-9018; Multivizion (Musical group) (Box 461)
        Situation 2
      - Act became real; The actors, 1981; SR-9019; Bollock Brothers. (Box 461)
      - Have you got EP, 1996; SR-9020; It Spy (Musician) (Box 461)
        Promotional copy
        Skint
      - What a remix. Vol. 5, 1992; SR-9021 (Box 461)
        What-A-Remix
      - Visage., 1981; SR-9022; Visage (Musical group) (Box 461)
      - Showdown, 1978; SR-9023; Isley Brothers. (Box 461)
      - Work me, 1988; SR-9024; God & The Prophets (Musical group) (Box 461)
        Hotlanta Records
      - Come let me love you, 1981; SR-9025; Day, Jeanette "Lady." (Box 461)
        Prelude Records
      - Come let me love you, 1981; SR-9026; Day, Jeanette "Lady." (Box 461)
        White label; promotional copy._x000D_
      - Sunshine, 1971; SR-9027; Flaming Ember (Musical group) (Box 461)
        Hot Wax
      - Age of electronicus, 1969; SR-9028; Hyman, Dick, 1927- (Box 461)
        Govinda
      - Slippin' away, 1978; SR-9029; Independent Movement (Musical group) (Box 461)
        "Promotional copy"; "For programming only".
      - Rhythm of life., 1977; SR-9030 (Box 461)
        Chiaroscuro
      - Disco train, 1976; SR-9033; Osmond, Donny. (Box 461)
        Polydor/Kolob Records
      - Natural high I., 1979; SR-9034 (Box 461)
        Chimneyville Records
        Jackson, Mississippi
      - K.C. and the Sunshine Band., 1975; SR-9035; KC & the Sunshine Band. (Box 461)
        T.K. Records
      - Strategy, 1979; SR-9037-9038; Bell, Archie, 1944- (Box 461)
        Philadelphia International Records